okay welcome to
nagarjuna course three
and uh we are going through
five years of nagarjuna
and uh i always wanted to translate his
greatest book
which is called wisdom or prazenya
and uh
so i just decided that during the long
run times
maybe i would give you guys some dessert
and you know what happens if you get too
much dessert
you get crazy
so we've been filming
uh nagarjuna number three it's going to
take five years to finish the garjana
and we're on the third year now and it's
going well
we are working on tony namas uh
commentary two good things happened
yesterday you guys going to ask me what
they were
number one
we found the
scan of tony loma's commentary that got
lost 20 years ago
that came from his own monastery from
chuni monastery
and so now i can actually check things
and it was the only copy in the world
and we can talk about that someday
and secondly
you ready
peace tree cafe got all its permits from
the county
after
after one and a half years of fighting
i almost had a heart attack
okay i don't know why they did it
but god blessed him okay so i'm feeling
good today
uh i thought that since a lot of you
guys are listening first of all i'd like
to thank you
for being the aci volunteer team and
working all over the world
and making things happen for aci and i'm
really really grateful you know
again
oh we got medicine volunteers too so i
was thinking what's a tasty
dish to serve up from peachtree cafe
for aci volunteers and
medicine buddha volunteers together you
know what's something delicious that i
can give you
because that's what a cafe owner has to
do right
so
i thought
a lot of you are in the gold clubs a lot
of you are helping to support
the project to save the ancient books it
will take about 700 years to save all
the books
and it will take about i don't know just
one book that we started this year it's
gonna take 51 years to finish i don't
know what's going to happen
uh
so
we've been working like that and i
thought that since a lot of you are
involved with acip or all
and how to save the books i thought
today maybe it would be fun to start out
with
you know
describing to you how i use it so i use
this database
about two or three hundred times every
day
for the last 35 years
and um
without it i couldn't it'd be very
difficult for me to teach
and what i'd like to do and we're sorry
our tech is not too high today i'm
holding one computer on my lap and
i'm facing it to this other computer
but i thought you'd like to see
what the database looks like because you
know a lot of you guys are
you know raising money
for
producing this database and maybe maybe
you've never seen it in use
and i sort of want to tie it into
nagarjuna today so this is a special
nagarjuna class
and during this version of nicaragua
which is very very difficult
we are tying it into
why does medicine buddha work okay why
do the mantras work you know how does
that tantra
work
and
if you understand
how the mantras work how the practice
works
then it's going to work a lot better
okay it's like a computer system if you
understand how it works
it can work better and if you don't
understand how it works you could end up
holding a computer on your lap to try to
get the
other screen to show
and so obviously
it's really useful to know how something
works so
if you understand
how the medicine for the practice works
uh
then you can do it a lot better and you
can get better results from it okay
and
we had a big discussion about it and
some people were saying
that doesn't matter how it works just
teach you how to do it
but i i do believe that if you know how
it works
it's more powerful you know if you're
like an old grandma somewhere
and you know you just want to do mantras
and you don't want to know how they work
that's okay
like i'm thinking about my mom she's 95.
you know maybe maybe i can't explain to
her how how the mantra works i can just
tell her just do the mantras
but if you understand how things work
they work better
okay so here's the database here's what
it looks like let's say
i i wanted to show you something about
the garjana
uh of course negotia's
thing is to explain emptiness the
guardian is most popular thing of all
time
is to explain emptiness of course
and i uh here's what the database looks
like
on my computer okay
and uh
here's the different parts of the
database that i use every day
and i wanted to take you i don't know
let's go to the tenure okay
this is uh 5 000 books
that were
translated into tibetan and the
translation fin it took 700 years
and they finished it around the time of
jetson kappa
and
you know it was it was four thousand
six or seven hundred books okay
and the first goal of ac of all uh 35
years ago
was to input uh all their ancient books
from india which is all the sutras and
all the commentaries and all the tantras
and the only problem was
there was no copy in india
of them they got they all got burned or
destroyed
and so the first job we had was to we
actually contacted
this ancient ancient monastery that
still had some blocks
and we actually got into the library
and we had the blocks
we had new pages printed from the blocks
you're talking about
three hundred and ten
thousand
blocks three hundred and ten thousand
blocks
to print all the things from the
kangaroo and tenure from ancient india
and we did it
we finished uh it took us about 10 12
years
and we typed uh about
uh it's about 310 000 pages and we did
it
and so
we have that that we can use so here's
tenure these are all the commentaries
from ancient india
and i wanted to here's all the
categories
of the tenure here
uh for example there's uh professional
wisdom
middleway
there's mind only there's abhidharma
there's nanaya
there's a logic
there's medicine
there's architecture
there's grammar
there's how to
there's books about how to do practical
things like run a government
or there's even a book in here about how
to grade gemstones
which i saw is fun for me i wanted you
to show you this category the second one
here which is called
vadriana right the diamond way
and as you can see it's almost
well it's 78 different volumes which
means 78 000 pages
of ancient commentaries
to the tantras the countries are about
500 000 pages but here you've got about
78 000 pages
of commentary to them
and uh
these are divided um and and by the way
the the arrangement of the badriana was
secret
and
me and venerable jigme figured it out
using an ancient commentary that we
found
and it was really a big big deal
that after
i don't know this was carved three four
hundred years ago
uh somebody figured out how they put the
tantras in in the order that they are
which is really awesome
and i i don't know if you can see but
here uh are the four
classes of tantra
there are four different levels of
tantra
for example medicine buddha is the
fourth level
and uh highest level is called anita
first level and let's go to anutara
here's uh i don't know
[Music]
different categories
of different anutar tantras for example
uh chakrasambaras here
kalachakra is here
one part of tara
is here
and
perhaps the highest tantrus is called
guia samaja
and this was the favorite of jetson
and this is also the one that's used for
the temple college where my teacher was
the director assistant director
uh in 1955
and
if you go inside of the guyasamaja
secret books
there's five huge categories
and hundreds of books and the first
category
is called ludo blue
which means uh the system of
nagarjuna okay
so people ask me hey did nagarjuna know
about tantra
hey
the highest part of the highest
standards
is nagarjuna
okay and it's all dedicated to him it's
volumes
uh dedicated to nagarjuna's
interpretation
of the diamond way okay so
and he's the first person mentioned in
the tenure so he's the greatest expert
not only about emptiness but he's the
greatest expert as you can see here
uh
in the secret teachings okay he's number
one okay
he was the highest
teacher
and his system was recorded and used in
ancient india and there still exists
a couple thousand pages of explanation
of his version
of the guhiya samadhi which is again
uh socopa's favorite
uh tantra that he used himself okay so
there's the books from ancient india
and the first great emphasis of the
secret teachings of the highest
class of the secret teachings
is negotiate system negotiate
presentation
which is very very beautiful okay
now suppose i want to see
uh if i'm working with the database and
i want to see
well what did
the tibetans the tibetans made a
thousand years of commentaries
what did they say
about nagarjuna's
treatment of of the secret way okay the
diamond was so then in the database i
would go to
which means here's all the tibetan
books and i don't know we have something
like 50 000 books
finished okay
and uh
here you can see i clicked on mojo
and
uh on the right
you can see all the books actually it's
all the shells
of our digital library that have mojos
there's about 150 lojos there okay
and by the way it took 35 years of
really hard work
first of all to find the books
then to input the books
and no one in history has has catalogued
them
nobody
and we cataloged them and it took 30
about 30 years of work
so you know we don't talk about it much
you guys probably never heard about it
but it took
thousands of hours of work
to put the library into order to put
everything on shelves to say oh
tantra's over here
middleweight is over here i'll be
donald's over there
and then to arrange all the shelves okay
it took many many thousands of hours
so let's go to tantra okay let's just
see
how did the tibetans
deal with tantra
okay so it happens to be
and by the way you can see all the
categories here vinaya
uh there's lineage trees there's history
books
way
uh
comparative philosophy of dharma
so let's go to tantra okay which is
called gute
and on the right you can see all of the
different tantric
systems okay and there's a hundred and
thirty
okay medicine buddha is one
all right and there's 129 others that we
have
preserved
okay uh so you know you can see here for
example manjushri
white manjushri
chakrasambara amitabha
and we have catalog
and we have saved
130 different schools of tantra
so medicine buddha is just one school of
tantra and then there's 129 others that
we have identified
and we have recovered
so if you if you look here let's go to
that uh
the garganous
presentation of the highest tundra okay
which is called guyasamaja
and it's right
here
and then you can see on the right
are all the different categories
of the cuya samaja all right
and uh
commentaries
uh
how did
how to move your mind on after you die
uh how to do the guru yoga how to do
retreat
how to do the empowerment how to draw
the mandala
how to make the tormas
uh
how to do the mantras uh how to do the
confession how to do the four powers
according to guys
how to do the fire offering
and in many many categories like that
okay so that's just
nagarjuna that's just negativeness
tantra
and let's check i there's a way look
let's see how many pages are there okay
uh
so it's um
seven million bytes
okay
call it uh
i don't know uh if you transfer it into
pages
uh
it's uh
7.5 megabytes
just on the gardener okay it's about uh
it's about 5000 pages okay 5 thousand
pages
of negotiations explanation
of the secret teachings why are we
talking about all this
uh well as maybe you noticed
uh the gardener
made the ritual that we used to take our
bodhisattva mouse
and without that ritual without some
ritual for the bodhisattva mouse you're
not allowed to study medicine buddha
okay you have to take an empowerment and
then you have to take the vows at least
about to try to be a bodhisattva
you have to take that you have to go
through that ceremony and we used
the guardians ceremony okay and now
today
we're to jump into the swimming pool
called nagarjuna and it's extremely
hard okay
and we're going to be jumping into
his teachings
on emptiness yes what's it got to do
with medicine buddha
well here's the search program for the
database okay we invented
this search program
uh
and i thought you'd like to see how it
works i'm gonna search
5 000 books from ancient india
i'm going to look for
any presentation
of chung chuki sam
of bodhichitta and i just use the part
of the name because it's
it's faster
and then i'm going to look at it near
his name naga did nagarjuna
write anything about
dodi chinner
why dislike why are you now why are you
off to bloody sitting now because i'm
irritated
why are you irritated because i'm
aggravated why are you aggravated
i talked to somebody yesterday they said
uh oh we we went on to medicine but we
don't need lumbering anymore you know
we're we're advanced now we don't have
to do lung room you know and i'm like
i got aggravated
you know
so
the person
who wrote
uh
8 000 pages
of commentary based on him
and some by him
on on the highest teachings of tantra
okay
did he study long rim
okay did he think long-range was still
important
or did he just go on to medicine okay
well here it is you can ask the database
hey database sorry
did uh
didn't the guardian i think uh buddhist
year was important
you know and then you can look you're
gonna search
uh
i don't know a million pages in one and
a half seconds you ready are you
watching here we go one two three
found
found it okay it took less than a second
of this
and there it is okay luduk means
nagarjuna
and here's the book called chanting to
send kevin
yes
he wrote a ritual
for taking the bodhisattva vows and it's
in the ancient books
did he write anything else
yeah he wrote this a commentary
on how to get bodhichitta he wrote a
commentary on bodhichit how to get
bodhichitta where is their commentary
located in the tantras
okay the guardian's commentary on how to
get bodhichitta
is tundra
okay it's in the tantras okay i didn't
say so they said so okay so
so there's now you've got 8 000 pages of
tantric commentaries and root texts
about nagarjuna's system on tantra maybe
he understands medicine today
you know
maybe he thought it was important to
take your buddy's alphabets as part of
tundra
okay he wrote the book
okay
okay so i just wanted to impress on you
guys there's a there's a huge connection
you've got to study long room
if you want to study tantra medicine
buddha
and especially the part of the alarm
room that deals with compassion and love
and especially
the part about emptiness okay you've got
to understand emptiness
or the mantra doesn't work okay you can
sit and do mantras all day but if you
don't understand
how something works
it doesn't work okay it's weird okay you
can say mantis it's okay you get a
little good karma
uh because of your motivation
but
if you go and fight your way
through negotiates presentation
emptiness
then you're really gonna understand
medicine buddha okay so we call this
program
uh the emptiness of medicine buddha and
let's jump into uh the emptiness of
medicine twitter okay and i say
it's the only way to make it work for
you really well okay
and i i don't know i'm excited to share
it with
all of you uh volunteers because i
figure you're the most serious people
um in the whole world
and i like serious people there's
there's a lot of people that if i say
let's fight our way through nagarjuna's
most difficult book about emptiness
because he understood tantra and he knew
it was necessary for medicine buddha
in fact
it's got 8 000 pages about his
understanding of tundra
in the database already
let's dig through it okay so i trust you
guys
uh
won't get confused or go crazy okay
we have to find our way deep through
emptiness
in the monastery
if the teacher can make you confused
about emptiness
they think it's progress
okay if you think you understand
emptiness after half an hour
you're wrong okay it takes
it took me about 20 years or something
so okay so
here we go we're gonna go to
our actual text today
this is our deep dive class number seven
and here we go
all right uncle tim are you ready with
uh
all right uh this chapter let's go to
the chapter name okay
uh by the way we're well into the text
already uh
this is called chapter 13
and it's an investigation of factors
now those sharp sharp guys among you
you should
tell grandpa wait we already did that in
chapter one
what was the name of chapter one
an investigation of
conditions
can she the four conditions
now there are 12 chapters later
he decides to cover
factors well what's the difference
between a factor and a condition okay
let's go back can you bring it up again
yeah duchenne means uh things that make
other things happen oftentimes duchenne
means secondary causes which is why i
translate it as factors for example
what's the main cause of a tree
is the seed that's called near langu
that's called the immediate cause
and then you have uh duchess which means
contributing factors like water sunlight
uh fertilizer okay what's stockpile
meaning guys this is the chapter
investigation
oops how do you say in sanskrit
okay looking all around the question
buddy
like periscope iksha which came into
germany's
alga which came into english as e y e
that's why there's a y
in the english word for your eyeball
okay so
each chapter of the 27 chapters of
negotiate most difficult and most
important word
called
no his book
just wisdom okay and that's so negative
you know he didn't say a discussion
of the details of wisdom he's somebody
asking what's your book name he said
wisdom
yeah but what wisdom but wisdom
you know and that's so negative okay
he
he's a man of few words okay
okay so
we're going to investigate how does one
thing cause another thing but
this particular chapter is not named
in an obvious way in this case
factors means illusion
okay so what's what's the connection
between one thing causing another thing
and the idea of an illusion maya maya
and illusion so really he should have
called this
maya pariksha
it's not really discussing the different
kinds of factors he did that already in
the first chapter
by chapter 13
he's talking about how do causes and
conditions how are they involved with
illusion
okay so here we go all right
put on your seat belt
all right
and by the way
uh he's not satisfied with covering
illusion at the end he covers tongniki
the emptiness of emptiness okay so you
guys
this morning you have bad luck you got
on a rocket shoot
okay uh we're gonna talk about the
emptiness of emptiness by the time we
finish today
and it and and i'll keep coming back to
the medicine bit of practice
and showing why if you understand
emptiness
you can
your mantras will be more powerful and
your practice will be more and you just
be super medicine for your guy okay
all right here we go
uh first verse
the buddha said every single thing in
the world lua cheats you
everything in the world cheats you
the mantras of medicine buddha also
cheat you
what
okay
then he everybody said why
why because zimba
they lie to you
they lie to you okay
everything in the world is cheating
why because they lied to you okay zumba
said the buddha now there's a very okay
i'm just gonna get you ready if you ever
get to the monastery
and you're ever debating in uh
colloquial tibetan at two thousand words
a second
uh somebody might bring up this
favorite topic
okay the buddha spoke lie
the buddha spoke
lies
and then okay
so the buddha doesn't follow the 10 good
deeds right what do you mean he broke
number four what's number four
he's lying okay the buddha spoke lies
okay and if you want to have a fun
debate with one of the 12 year olds
at the monastery this is good for like
an hour and a half or somethin
here's here's where he spoke life okay
in the garden that he spoke less but
what does it really mean
he said all all things which have causes
are
lying to you so he just mentioned the
word lying he didn't speak a lie
he spoke
lies
but he didn't say a lie okay got it it's
a joke
all right if you're ever debating with
the 12 year olds you know
everything that has a cause or
everything that is across is lying to
you
therefore
sorry
everything that has a cause is cheating
you therefore they are liars jimba okay
they are liars okay this is uh
this is how nagarjuna starts to
start the
chapter and that's why we had tim and
grandpa
in the picture
at the beginning of the class okay
and the idea is that
i don't know
the uh
that the employee is cheating
the the employer i guess
and uh he got caught okay so
the idea is uh the employee is cheating
the employer and therefore he will have
to
lie to the employee okay so there's a
connection between cheating and lying
okay he stole the money which is
cheating and now he's gonna have to lie
about it to keep the money all right all
right so just get in that mood we're
talking about illusion we're talking
about somebody lying to you okay all
right let's go to the next verse tim
hmm
okay i agree
so suppose everything's cheating
[Music]
oh then what's it lying about you know
then how how do things including
medicine buddha practice
and including medicine buddha mantra how
are they lying to me okay how are they
lying to me
look he said they are lying to you and
that got him into the subject of tongi
emptiness okay wow what do you mean
well
the honesty of that employee's
transaction
don't exist
okay he's cheating the company okay how
much honesty is in his transaction
how much honesty is going on at that
desk at that moment
zero and that's called emptiness got it
when somebody lies to you
there's no reality there then the
situation is empty
of reality okay when someone cheats you
they lie to you when they lie to you the
truth is gone and that's a kind of
emptiness okay if it's not real
it's empty okay buddha said
things that cheat you lie to you
everything around you is cheating you
everything around you including medicine
buddha mantras is lying to you
and therefore it's all empty there's no
truth there nothing's real
okay got it
all right
then i i don't know when i ch okay i was
trying to find a picture about lying
here it is
all right it's a gucci bag
that you buy in thailand on the street
okay
for two dollars there's a place in oh no
it's in beijing there's a special market
uh my friend went crazy my friend from
israel he went he went to this market he
bought like 30 gucci bags for all his
relatives
and uh they're each like a dollar and i
don't know you pick them up and the
handle falls off and
stuff like that okay so it looks like a
gucci bag
but it's a fake gucci bag okay and the
buddha said everything around you is
like that everything's lying to you okay
all right let's go to the next verse
oh sorry i'm gonna i'm gonna throw a
quotation in that's not in your
okay
um
so when did the buddha talk about
lying right supposedly the buddha has
talked about lying
so can you show me the quotation and
choni lama takes the challenge
and he says i'll show you the i got a
quotation buddha talked about it and
it's called
matrimpa means a special lake
that will never dry up tropa mistria
which means uh
sometimes it's called not warm
but there's a naga living in the lake
his name is
okay
and uh
sometimes they call it not warm or warm
and
he's having a conversation with lord
buddha in this sutra okay it's the sutra
of the naga in the lake
there's our conditions okay anything
that comes from causes and conditions
like seeds or water or fertilizer
anything that's born from
water
and seeds is never born
anything that is born from water and
seeds is not born
buddhism it's all fake
it's all lie okay
there's no nature of being born there
nothing's being born there's no the
slightest bit of being born there
i tell you
anything that's mixed up with causes is
empty
it's a lie okay the truth is gone
kashi
anybody who really understands that
can do stuff well like medicine buddha
practice okay
you know means
like a newborn like a new red woman or
something like that it means they are
skillful they are
living in the right way okay anyone who
understands emptiness
is doing a good medicine better practice
okay that who said that the buddha said
that
why because they understand the illusion
there okay they understand that there's
emptiness there and that's where the
buddha described lies
okay anything that has a cause is lying
to you if you get it
then you can live a good life
you can have a good practice okay
all right i went and challenged for you
i'll put it in the translation
by the way translation is already 400
pages and it's it's tough it's a really
tough
and we're going through it at about 110
miles an hour okay
it should take like 20 years
all right here we go next verse
it's really a verse and a half by the
way
and
what did i say is tricky about reading
nagashina what did i say this could trip
you up you never know
yeah sometimes he sprinkles in the other
guy's comments and he doesn't warn you
there's no warning you know and you need
channing lama to tell you yeah no no he
this is not nightmare this is the other
guy
so here's the other guy
okay here's the other guy okay
man if stuff doesn't have a true nature
of its own
if things don't have a true nature of
their own when the guardian says they
don't by the way right
he says if things don't have a true
nature of their own
shenandoah then why do they change
and by the way the example is going to
be when you use milk to make yogurt and
in india
the way you make yogurt in the market is
uh
you you get a bowl of
milk hot milk you put in the yeast from
the last yogurt
and then you hang it up in your shop and
the flies cover it for the whole day you
can't even see the white color it's all
black
and then they serve it the next day
uh yeah
and
when i got back from india the doctor
told me i had 17 kinds of parasites and
uh so anyway
the milk
transforms into yogurt can you tell the
difference between the yogurt and the
milk
yeah it's different it tastes different
it's much it's sticky
he says the other guy says an
interesting thing he says look
if things that have causes have no
nature of their own then how can they
change
okay if the milk was not
if the milk didn't have an identity then
how did it drop that identity and become
yogurt
[Music]
right got it okay so according to you
nagarjuna
if everything's empty
and it has no nature of its own
then milk can never change okay because
it has to have a nature to change
it it has to be something before it can
change to something else
if it's not something in the first place
how can it become yogurt
okay all right shendu and nonchito we
can see things change
therefore it's not true that nothing has
any nature of its own me
it's not true that things have no nature
okay
no no
how can it become yogurt
how can it drop its former identity and
take on a new identity if it never had
an identity
this is the other guy okay talking to
the guy
all right and if you don't know what's
the other guy you're in trouble
right okay
all right and i i found a picture that i
like uh
it's leaves green and and different
colored leaves it's i don't know
it's springtime here we're thinking
about these and
if the leaf wasn't green how could it
turn yellow
got it
if the leaf wasn't green
how could it turn yellow in the garjana
you said nothing has any nature of its
own
okay i did so leaves aren't green
what's it got to do
well if they're not green how can they
turn yellow then how can you say turn
okay they must be green those those
green leaves are green
right they have a nature they're green
if they didn't have a nature they
couldn't become yellow
it makes sense right
got it
yes you are you're correct okay
all right here we go
uh next verse
and
and the gardener's answer is no
if things did have a nature how could
you
okay the other guy said if green leaves
aren't green how can they turn to yellow
and then the gardener says if green
leaves were green they couldn't turn to
yellow
your argument defeats yourself
okay if green leaves are green they
can't become yellow leaves they're green
you can't call it yellow for green leaf
come on if a green leaf was really green
it couldn't become yellow
so don't give me this stupid example
that because things change they must
have had some nature because you
couldn't say they changed if they didn't
have a nature in the first place to
change prom
got it you okay just keep nodding
you guys at home just keep nodding i
know okay
so he uses the argument back to the
other guy
you know if it was if green leaves are
green
then they can't become yellow at least
because they're green leaves
got it okay he uses the same argument
back to the guy here's the picture
okay
this picture was easy okay if green
leaves are green they can never be
yellows duh
okay if green leaves had in nature
of being green they could never become
yellows okay
the other guy said if they don't have a
nature of being green
how can you observe a change
in them if they if they drop that nature
and become yellow
okay got it so they must have had me
all right now uh chonie lama uses a very
beautiful word here
and i want to use it for our sanskrit
lessons so every regards in the class we
have
we're gonna do a mini sanskrit
lesson okay so you gotta learn a little
bit of sanskrit don't worry it won't
hurt you
it's like 15 words for the whole course
but since you have to speak in sanskrit
later after the medicine buddha practice
which has no nature makes you a medicine
buddha
you're gonna have to speak sense okay so
you might as well get used to it now all
right it's like you're going to
guadalajara and muzzle learned about
five words it makes the taxi driver so
happy
okay
all right
so here we go uh you got that one for me
you guys
this is our little sanskrit method uh
this is a word called by the way i
misspelled it there tim is it too late
to fix it prakriti
it should be a k-i-r this is an old
mistake that everyone else makes
okay prakerty and and those of you may
have heard it okay you've probably heard
this prakriti it's a very famous word in
hindu yoga schools
okay it's a very famous idea
in tibetan
it's called shilok okay
and that she is a very unusual word that
means the primordial nature of something
okay she
and it happens to be used in a famous
expression
which means are you having a good
primordial nature
okay
okay and that's how you say hi in
tibetan you say
which means
wonderful primordial shining nature
thank you
like when you say thank you in tibetan
what does it mean
your great heart
your holy your great holy heart is how
you say thank you
okay and how you say uh good morning
is a shining primordial nature of
happiness and goodness
okay which used to be the expression for
happy new year
and then it became so common that people
started using it for good morning
all right uh
prakriti
comes from prague the prefix lighter
product
and then kurti okay and by the way
people say prakriti and it's wrong the
pronunciation is wrong okay
uh prakrit people say prakrit and that's
like saying uh
it's like your german friends who say i
went and bought a cheap
and drove it home
you know
it's just a mistake of pronunciation
okay
all right so pra means forward
or very much
cur is the verbal root that means to
make or to do
uh
as we spoke about pram many times kerr
we spoke about it's found in serial
create and karma
and the c in cereal used to be a k okay
it changed around the time of
shakespeare
uh
and then ta
makes it a an
a past tense okay
and i think it came into english with ed
means
that which was made from the beginning
and it means the original nature of an
object in in sankhya philosophy in
ancient hindu
yoga philosophy
they will
juxtapo
juxtapose two things
miss
okay so purusa
means uh
the person
and it means god
the person capital p who made everything
and then prakrti is the nature which was
made by the god okay so
in hinduism
uh especially in the ancient yoga
philosophy prakrti is nature
and purusa is the creator
but in buddhism pakurti means the nature
which things cannot have
the original nature green leaf
green green is in the lake okay like
that so try to remember that that's
called shibu okay
and choni lama is very skillful to use
the word
so now today you you used you learned a
new word what
that which was made in the beginning
okay and the nature of him
when michael was
made by his parents
was he made with a nature built in from
the factory
you know did he have a nature for cookie
in him from from the factory okay from
my mom factory
okay all right here we go next subject
he just jumps on you you know hey you
guys talking about change right greenlee
changes yellow right yeah yeah yeah does
that have a nature
that's the changing heaven nature
got it
forget the leaf now
did the green leaf have a nature we say
no they say yeah
they say it had to have a nature because
it
changed
if it didn't have an identity how could
it take on a new identity of being
yellow how could milk change itself drop
its old identity and become yogurt right
if it didn't have an identity in the
first place now we say by the way you
guys want to talk about the emptiness of
change
you know when the yogurt when the milk
becomes yogurt when the leaf turns to
yellow
what's the emptiness of that okay
de nilo okay if things
uh have a primordial nature for kurti
shangri or men they cannot change to
something else
if things are self-existently separate
they can't have a nature okay if things
are self-existent and separate or other
is the yellow leaf different from the
greenlee
yeah it's yeah okay it's the yogurt
different look
yeah it's that different stuff exactly
that's a this gun kanji or shin amigate
young people don't get old and old
people don't get old either
that's negan
young people don't get old and old
people don't get old either okay now
let's do the second one because it's
easier
do old people get old no they're already
old
okay
okay we got that one finished now the
big question is do young people get old
no cause they're young people
okay listen
do young people get on no
why
yeah it's different it's totally
different
do all people get old no they're audio
do young people get older no they're
young
and you got it
quit flowing around with the words i'm
not floating around with words i'm
trying to demonstrate to you that words
are messed up already and you don't
notice it
okay
what are you talking about
young old old an old young person
well what do you mean okay something's
wrong the mantra cured the cancer the
medicine with a mantra
killed the cancer okay what's the
connection
the mantra never touched the cancer
how could it create cancer are they
separate or not
okay
how does milk become show
means yogurt okay if you ever need
if you're ever hungry ask for some show
okay
but say low tone show
don't say show show means dice and it
means you want to play some you want to
lose some money
don't say i'm hungry i need some show
show okay so omanini
all malaysian crushing
is the
milk
separate from yogurt or not
are they separate things
yes or no don't don't i'm not tricking
you
that's here's the guy in a typical
negotiation hey i'm not tricky
just answer the question
is the milk the yogurt
are they separate
yeah do they ever touch
cannot
why
the the milk was yesterday
the yogurt is today okay
they can't overlap
if the
if they touch
at any point
then yesterday is today
it's not possible okay your milk cannot
turn into you
it's not possible something's weird is
going on
medicine but a mantra cannot cure cancer
but it does
and that's how we get yogurt right how
many times you ate yogurt must be
something
all right
next oh i have a picture of a grandma
and a granddaughter
the granddaughter is not getting the
granddaughter is not
old
and uh i'm getting old
and the grandma's not getting old
because the grandma already got home
and the daughter is young
okay all right go figure
next next one who in this class is
now according to channing lama who's
guiding us and by the way i haven't had
we haven't gone through the commentary
commentary would take about 20 years to
teach really and it's beautiful
but uh
he warns us
i'm going to prove to you
that emptiness doesn't have a nature of
its own
okay i'm gonna prove to you that
emptiness is empty all right and that's
his that's his big thing
uh
the next verse
is one of the most famous verses of this
whole book and uh it's it's kind of an
honor that we have all our medicine
buddha and aci volunteers here today
because we hit
maybe the most well second most famous
verse from this whole book okay and it's
just cool that you're here
because
in five years it's only going to happen
once okay so here we go
if there's anything that's not empty if
there's the slightest thing which is not
empty
you could have the slightest thing which
isn't
okay if there's the slightest thing
which isn't empty
then you can have the slightest bit of
emptiness
okay
don't mean
if there isn't the slightest thing which
is not empty
how could you have emptiness
okay you you need the opposite to define
a thing
okay if there's no such thing as not
being empty how are you going to
recognize emptiness
you you recognize things by comparison
to other things okay how do you know
something's blue it's not yellow
you know
you compare if
if blue was around you all the time if
everything in your world was blue you
wouldn't see the blue
i mean you'd be looking at it but you
wouldn't see it
okay
so
this is a very very famous uh proof
that emptiness has its own emptiness
okay
now how how is that
let's look at this picture
this is a glass of water which is
completely full
it's definitely not empty
uh but there would have to be some part
of non-empty
if the emptiness came from its own side
okay
if
if emptiness came from its own side
there would have to be part which is not
empty therefore that last statement was
who was talking
sounds like the other guy okay sounds
like the other guy
you know okay nightmare so must be some
stuff if if things don't have an
identity of their own
then the only way you're gonna recognize
it is by looking at the opposite
therefore there must be some things in
the universe that aren't empty and you
can compare them to the things that are
empty and you can tell they're empty
okay otherwise how could you ever see if
emptiness didn't have its own nature
if it were only empty by comparison
all right okay here we go if you're not
confused yet we'll work on it
[Music]
let's go to the next verse okay
uh gawa nam
[Music]
this is a very subtle verse
it takes a lot of work
i'll i'll
i'll introduce it to you and what my
teacher said was you have to cook it
rebecca used to sit with my teacher so
right did you cook it
we said no no we don't understand it's a
cookie goddamn cookie
i'm going home
i should try that okay
that the victors stated about emptiness
first principle path
is renunciation but
uh it also means to rip something out
uh to rip something
pull it out okay pull yourself out of
the home like
it's called renunciation but here
uh
the the buddha said that emptiness rips
out
wrong
if you get emptiness
it will renunciate
your wrong views pull them out of the
house get out
this house
this is very subtle okay
whosoever sees emptiness
whosoever thinks they see emptiness
being from its own side okay that's the
trait
whosoever sees emptiness
dead due to memphis this droop means
fixable
repairable
man
what's the biggest mistake you can make
in life if you think that emptiness has
its own nature
then you are hopeless truly hopeless who
said that soon the buddha okay
okay if you think the mantra is gonna
work from his own side
you are hopeless totally hopeless okay
like it's better you didn't hear the
mantra
you know if you're gonna grab onto the
mantra it's working from its own side
and you don't need to save
life for the mantra to work
okay if you think the mantra is going to
work from its own side without saving
life
then
you know you're going to have same
mantras without saving life
good luck you know
you're hopeless okay who said that
but uh
during the melbourne here means
you know you are broken and no one can
fix you
why because you're using the dharma
already but you're using it wrong okay
so you're you're the worst kind of
broken
and i i can't do anything for you i
can't fix you who said that
buddhism
pretty heavy okay
so that uh finishes our class today
again it's a
special treat class suffering for
uh those of you who have been helping so
much and i i know
i helped my llama for 30 years i washed
dishes for 30 years me and ellie found a
picture of us
shoveling snow outside you know when it
used to snow before the
global warming and uh
and you know that was the whole day was
like that so i
i gotta tell you
that uh
being a volunteer
is the coolest smartest thing you can do
really honestly i'm not just selfish
okay
and i did it for 30 years and and i look
back at those times
some of my friends from princeton used
to say that guy's taking advantage of
you
you know you're working all day for free
and you could be a big lawyer and or you
could be a big government official
they're all dead now
or they got cancer and they write me
letters every day all day
help me help me you know i don't know
what to do you know teach me something
you know and these guys told me when i
went to my teacher you're a fool
to uh spend all day volunteering for
your teacher but but i look back at
those where
i look back at those days
and i was really really happy okay those
were the happiest days of my life so
uh you're very smart to be a volunteer
and uh keep going
and you look back at these days and
you'll say oh that was the best time
all right see you later